[Music]
the red pill was one of the most
polarizing documentaries of recent years
it showed self-described feminist cassie
j going inside the men's rights movement
in the US where she changes her mind
about feminism the conversation is being
silenced for a society to accept
anything said on behalf of women's
rights and then to shame any dialogue
about men's rights and call it hate
speech is precisely the problem I don't
know where I'm headed but I know what I
left behind I no longer call myself a
feminist a word-of-mouth hit it also
provoked protests some extremely
critical reviews and was even banned
from some cinemas in Australia so you
brought out the red pill is it two years
three years ago now yeah two tears and
so there's one thing there's the film
itself and I'd love to talk to you about
that and your journey about making it
and then there's another thing which is
the reaction to the film why I'm really
interested in that is that it shows a
lot about the cultural moment that we're
in when I watched the film as a
filmmaker I I had a slight suspicion or
just I wondered like how authentic the
journey was because it was very like the
narrative was was sort of very powerful
you came in as a feminist and then work
were sort of your mind was changed by
the stories that you heard and you came
out with a very different experience and
I we interviewed Warren Farrell recently
in in America and I sort of said that to
him I was like well you know Cassie and
how authentic was that journey and he
said no it's completely authentic and
told me a little bit about the backstory
of what you were telling him as you were
going through it so I'd love to hear
more about that journey that you went
through him making it I appreciate you
being honest that you're skeptical of is
this girl for real was she really a
feminist and then sort of questioned her
beliefs after talk
men's rights activists and I think I
would have had the same reaction if I
didn't make the red pill movie and I
watched it as a feminist I think I would
have been very skeptical well first of
all I don't know if I would have watched
the red pill movie seeing how the media
was talking about the film but yeah I
definitely would have been skeptical
because it is such a sensational idea
for a story for a documentary and it's
almost too strange to be true but yeah
it was actually kind of a suicide
mission for me where I had a hundred
hours of footage after filming men's
rights activist for a year and but
working on the film for three and a half
years and I I knew the journey that I
went on was going to make me extremely
vulnerable and open to critique and
debate and and probably a lot of people
would question you know
Who am I and am I true and in my video
diaries and and my interviews and all
that and even men's rights activists
were questioning me as a documentary
filmmaker going in to interview them so
really everyone was wondering is this
chick for real so yeah I knew in making
the film there was gonna be a lot of
skepticism about me and I I just figured
while I have to put it out there and
whatever happens happens and I I say it
was a suicide mission because if it
completely flopped and failed knowing
that I put the raw real journey out
there then as well as having this stigma
now against my name being a part of this
highly controversial topic for a film I
would have to go into hiding in it and I
resolved that in my head as well I can
just become a mother I'm already a
hermit anyways I'm I'm a homebody so I
was willing to take that risk and and
luckily the film really resonated with a
lot of people around the world so I'm
I'm glad I took that risk could you
describe that journey and what you went
through what were your intentions going
into it what happened during it and and
where did you end up
well my attentions going into it were I
mean it talks a little bit about it in
the film I was looking into the rape
culture topic for a documentary and what
really made me decide not to do a film
about that was because it was so
depressing when I started looking into
the stories that I could cover and I I
didn't know if I could put years of my
mental headspace into that topic by when
when I was trying to figure out the
cause of the feminist view of rape
culture I was pointed towards the men's
rights movement and at the time a voice
for men this online hub of men's rights
activists was the largest and fasting
fastest growing men's rights movement
online and they were definitely the most
controversial with Polly Elam being The
provocateur of the movement and I
thought well this is interesting and I I
researched and found that no one had
ever made a film on men's rights
movement before it was fairly a young
movement still so I thought I was gonna
be the first and it was going to be a
shocking piece and it would be a
feminist going undercover into this
misogynistic world and I would expose
them for who they really are and and
really that's what I thought the film
was going to become and sure enough as I
started interviewing men's rights
activists I knew that that idea that I
had of men's rights activist was not the
truth of who they really were and what
they cared about or why they were part
of the men's rights movement and so then
I had to put my own agenda aside and
really start to listen to what they had
to say and why they care about this
movement and and ask myself is there
still a story here and there were
definitely moments while I was filming
and editing I was wondering well who's
gonna care about you know father's
rights and suicide rates and male
victims of domestic violence do we
really have of all the issues in the
world is this worth someone's two hours
of their time to watch the documentary
and the more I really started to dig
into it I realized
is a huge pervasive issue all throughout
the world with gender relations and and
what's happening for men opting out of
marriage and you know the MiG town
movement and feminism kind of dominating
the the pop culture and the media and
obviously I began to see that with the
release of the film so I didn't know
quite the extent until the film was
released how much the average person's
view of gender politics is really the
the feminist ideology of gender politics
so I and I think what really intrigued
me was how when I started to realize how
bias
I was against men's issues and my
knee-jerk reaction to wanting to dismiss
them or victim blame male victims of
domestic violence for instance I
I realized that wow this is a lot deeper
than that I thought I really do
appreciate that you told me that you're
skeptical of my journey making the film
and whether or not it was a scripted
plan for sensationalism and you know
even if I never made the red pill movie
and I just went on the journey of
filming all these men's rights activists
and questioning my own beliefs I I
really do believe that I benefited from
going going on that journey especially
in my own relationship and also
understanding my father figures and male
friends better I think I could have been
more private about my evolved views and
maybe that would have saved me some
stress over the past few years but
because I chose to take my
transformation public and show it and in
this film it really kind of you know I
guess I asked to be on the stage for
stones to be thrown and
I'm glad that I did it I hope I know
that it helps a lot of people making
this film and and but I don't think it's
I don't think we're anywhere near where
we need to be and I think the red pill
movie was just a very early kind of
icebreaker into these conversations but
I think we have a long way to go with
gender relations and and hopefully
eventually finding a healthier
relationship between the genders but
mostly for children a lot of men's
rights activists I'm hearing are
becoming very anti marriage and kind of
in the sense that McDowell is men going
their own way our anti marriage a lot of
men's rights activists are also moving
in that direction because they believe
the institution of marriage is so
corrupt and divorce courts are so
corrupt that they don't want to engage
in all in it at all and the the danger
and that is children because I I think
we're men's rights activists don't are
contradictory in their views as if
they're anti marriage but they also
stress the importance of present father
figures father to child connection you
need marriage to strengthen that
relationship and men's rights activists
have done a lot of work and even non
men's rights activists have done a lot
of work in showing the importance of
present father figures and the danger of
single mothers and I I would like to see
marriage valued and and looked at from a
scientific standpoint of building a
healthy society rather than from a
religious origin because I'm not
religious and I wouldn't even call
myself a traditionalist but I do think
marriage is a very important part of the
backbone of our society for children so
I think we need a look in that direction
helped to move in it in that direction
you kind of had your focus on gender
issues just before the me to movement
started but in a way you took precisely
the opposite perspective to to where the
culture was going and I say yes I did
yeah
the me to movement really got traction a
few months after the film's release so
there was no way I could know that that
was going to be the parallel media story
along with the red pills release so that
was interesting and I would have loved
to have commented on that movement if I
knew that was going to be coming your
background I mean we talked a little bit
before the cameras were rolling and you
described herself as you live in
California you're you're a liberal I
mean can you sort of sketch out where
you're from and and and what your
personal sort of background is sure oh
well I live in the San Francisco Bay
Area sorry I live in the San Francisco
Bay Area and I grew up in Seattle I went
to high school in Las Vegas I lived in
Los Angeles for about five years in the
film industry pursuing acting at the
time I never really made it I was a
horrible actress but I did a lot of
horror films in LA before moving up to
the Bay Area to continue documentary
filmmaking and I grew up fairly radical
image a local Christian and now I
consider myself agnostic but I left the
church around my late teens around 20
and around that time as I was leaving
the church I was also becoming a
feminist and and that was when social
media was kind of really taking off
around 2000 5 6 7
and I think social media had a lot to do
with me becoming a feminist just seeing
those little info memes and getting
sound bites of you know the pay gap
which at the time I was eating up and
believing and so I became an online
feminist and and for about ten years I
was a feminist before I started making
the red pill movie and you at the end of
the film you say you no longer consider
yourself a feminist how what what did he
mean by that and how would you describe
what it means to say that well that that
was definitely one of the biggest
question marks in my whole journey
making the film was do I keep the label
feminists and try to work within the
movement to make it more inclusive of
men's issues because after learning
about all these issues there's no way to
then walk through the world ignoring
that they exist I mean making the film
and probably for viewers watching the
film you can never see the world the
same way again so I thought do I keep
the title or the label feminist to try
to work within the movement kind of like
a christina hoff sommers the factual
feminist and of course you know I've
seen with her that it doesn't matter if
she calls herself a feminist the the
mainstream press will say what they
wanted her and feminists will disown her
and say you're not with us so I realized
I'm just one person in my late 20s at
the time I don't think I have the power
to work with in a very giant highly
funded movement to try to make it more
inclusive immense issues and so I
decided to drop the label feminist I
[Music]
think that's a good question why I mean
I think I also I think I wanted to see
how people would react I live in the Bay
Area where all my friends and family
consider themselves feminists and it's
kind of a a given I mean the the idea is
that if you're for gender equality then
you're a feminist and it's you can't
have one without the other and
so that I knew that their labeling
themselves feminists based on you know
what they're reading and mostly liberal
publications and and so I thought well
if I make the red pill movie and I share
with them because really in a one dinner
conversation I cannot explain to them
the journey I went on so hopefully I can
make a film to at least be an icebreaker
to these conversations and it did open a
lot of their eyes and minds to
considering men's issues but still many
of them remained feminists identifying
but some of them have gone on their own
kind of rabbit little journey after
watching the film and and started to see
some of the male bashing by feminist
scholars or educators or the media and
started to question well is feminism
really the movement the one and only
movement for gender equality and you
know personally for me I would want to
be a part of a movement for gender
equality that includes men and boys in
in the discussion and I think the first
step is to raising awareness about these
issues which feminism is not doing so I
dropped the label feminists I'm not a
men's rights activists at all I
understand their movement and sympathize
with their cause I think what they're
doing is valuable today I don't know I I
hope it won't be necessary
15 20 50 years from now but right now I
think it is necessary to have this
counterbalance in the gender political
discussion but I'm not a men's rights
activist and what was the reaction among
your friends and kind of your immediate
circle did you have any pushback or did
he lose any friends I lost some friends
and in a fade out kind of way where they
they heard about the red pill or they
saw many imprinted and didn't like what
they read and thought that I'd become
some crazy right winger or something
which I'm not I'm still a registered
Democrat and and I can it hurt myself a
liberal but I've been printed alongside
its white supremacist nationalists and
you know if I read that about some one
of my friends a few years ago back when
I was a feminist I would have been
alarmed too and thought well someone
went off the deep end went crazy you
know put him in a padded room and I
think that's what many of my friends
thought happened to me when we spoke to
Warren Farrell in America recently he
said that you came to him and said oh
are people gonna turn against me and he
said yes they are and at the time you
were like I was looking for some
reassurance and you're you're not giving
it to me yeah I mean a lot of the men so
it's activists and I don't think Warren
Federal Ferrell considers himself a
men's rights activists but but a lot of
the people I talk to during making the
red pill movie did warn me that I would
be career suicide that I would lose
friends and colleagues and and at the
time I thought they were being overly
dramatic and I I just thought the whole
movement was had all these conspiracies
that were unrealistic and maybe wanting
to you know get thing on their movement
riled up to excite people or feel like
they were part of some underground
secret society and so I really kind of
brushed it off and didn't think much of
it but sure enough years later a lot of
their premonitions were correct
what what do you make of the media
response because I sort of looked online
and quite a few that there's some really
harsh criticisms of the film sort of
especially from some of those sort of
more maybe millennial outfits like Vox
and Vice and all of those people that
maybe put some quotes and on-screen here
but what did he make of that response I
mean it was really hard at the time you
know I'm I take a lot of things you know
personally I'm a fairly sensitive person
and you know emotional at times and so
whenever an article is published that's
scathing of me or the film based on
misinformation it's infuriating to me
because I it's obvious they didn't do
their due diligence as
us to really research and and I know the
how the snowball started and and then
saw it rolling down the hill and it
started with our very first review of
the red pill movie in the Village Voice
based on radical feminist bloggers blog
and the misinformation he posted about
me and the men's rights movement and so
that is what had everything spiral out
of control and how the the red pill was
publicized and all the petitions against
the film and the justifications for
banning the film in Australia and Canada
were all based on these lies and it just
made me lose a lot of faith in the media
and also you know social media and the
power and and danger of groupthink and
thought police and and I and I also
acknowledged that I used to be a part of
that and how easily I could have fallen
into that had I never made this film
myself and I don't know if anyone else
would have made the film I would like to
think someone out there is gonna be
making more films about these topics
because I think they need to be talked
about but if I never made the red pill
movie I would have been right alongside
those other feminists trying to ban this
film and based on misinformation whether
any of the criticisms of the film that
you think were justified hmm that's a
very good question
of course the you know my argument is
time constraints is very you know
there's only so much you can do with
what I was aiming for hour and a half
long film became 2 hours so I was
already stretching it kind of long but
there's never enough time to include
everything and and one of I think one
criticism that I would give credit to is
how the red pill movie portrays feminism
and it wasn't a you know malicious
intentional effort to you know make
feminism look any kind of way I actually
think I have far more rational and level
had a feminist but most people going to
the movie theater to watch the red pill
only remember big red with the bright
red hair and so they think that's the
only discussion of feminism is her as
the as the the front of the movement and
I didn't see it that way I think she's
just very memorable but I don't think
that's the you know of all the content
included in the film there's a lot of
other scholars that are feminists that
talk about their views on the men's
rights movement and feminism but I also
didn't see the need to have a whole
history lesson on feminism because there
are for my one red pill movie
documentary there's a thousand or more
feminist documentaries that you can
watch on the same online platforms so to
take up - to take up time from the one
and only documentary on the men's rights
movement to date to take time out of
that to discuss the history of feminism
I I think would have been stolen time so
the criticism was that it was a
caricature of feminism because it was
mainly through this character at big red
is that yeah there was criticism that
feminism moment wasn't portrayed in a
positive light that that more
level-headed feminists would have liked
to see but you know we did have the
executive editor of news magazine who's
certainly very powerful in there and the
feminist majority foundation and and in
universities nationwide Michael Kimmel
is very influential feminist author
Michael Messner is a gender studies
professor i USC and you know I had
feminist friends included in the film so
protesters as well of course the big red
hat to be in there because she was the
only feminist that had a run-in with
men's rights activists face to face and
so it was a kind of a historical
milestone for the men's rights movement
to have this one and only interaction
between feminists and men's rights
activists at an event so I had to be
included and I was lucky enough to get
an interview with her so you know I also
got criticism for including Paul Elam in
the film which if I didn't include Paul
Elam in the film I would see that as a
Aled criticism because he's the most
known men's rights activists at least at
the time when I was filming and why
wouldn't you go to the source of all the
controversy and so there there's even
student groups who have screened the red
pill movie and then have been banned
from pride parades and participating and
other events just because they screen
the red pill movie which had Paul Elam
in it so it wasn't the movie itself that
was the problem but the fact that Paul
Elam was in the film was the problem so
there's just no way to win is the thing
on you know I maybe eventually there
will be a sequel who knows or another
filmmaker I hope will be interested in
tackling the men's rights movement and
they can do their own treatment of how
they lay the issues out there or the
members but you know it's good to
critique films though because that's
that's what you wanted as a filmmaker is
conversation do you think with with
Pauly Lam you could have been a little
bit more hard on him I mean my sense
watching the film was that as you just
said before you're not really a
confrontational kind of person and I'm a
journalist so I'm kind of used to kind
of confrontational style of interviewing
not that I particularly enjoy doing it
that way myself but like I did come away
thinking you didn't maybe ask some hard
questions - Pauly Lam but it that but I
got the sense that was your interviewing
style you didn't really ask but you
didn't really put anyone on the spot on
either side and I but I guess that was
and I know now that you weren't even
sure like why you were gathering the
interview you haven't really made up
your mind about what you thought about
any of them you were still in that
process well I think it's good to
distinguish between a Barbara Walters
type interview and a documentary and my
history and documentary filmmaking has
actually been flying the wall and so
rarely if ever my my voice has ever
heard in the film so the red pill was
the first film I ever included myself in
the film at all in including as
narrator and also asking a few questions
but very few questions that I asked my
interview subjects were included in the
final film itself so for people who
criticize that I didn't ask
harder-hitting questions to Paul Elam or
to feminists or to big red eyed you know
all the questions that I did ask them in
my two to five hour long interviews work
cut out except for maybe one question so
to criticize the questions I asked is
you know a hundred questions I asked
them ones shown in the film I think you
have to acknowledge the format of a
documentary especially when it's more
fly-on-the-wall but you know it's I did
release a lot of the raw footage of the
red pill movie so I really stood on
YouTube for free for people to watch to
see if I edit in anything out of context
or try to manipulate the way someone was
portrayed and I think that really helped
in showing that I did not have creative
manipulation in my editing style so if
anyone is wondering if I was
hard-hitting enough to appalled a limb
or anyone else they can watch the raw
files so yeah but as far as being more
confrontational I think I was really
confrontational in the raw files that's
just a matter of if it made it into the
final film because of all the that the
people in the film the one that the
people do keep coming back to his Paul
Elin and there are some things that he
said like I find really difficult online
like I've got a lot of sympathy with
with with the men's rights perspective
that it is something that's not really
seen or part of the conversation but
when I see him saying things like I
would definitely let off and I would
never find someone guilty in a rape
trial for example I just think this is
kind of difficult to defend yeah and you
know I could have I could have gone
through all the cherry-pick comments
that are used to against Paul Elam and a
voice for men and I think that would be
a film I wouldn't want to watch because
it'd be really boring it I think it's a
valid piece to put on on
people are really interested although I
think that people who need to hear it
wouldn't sit through two hours of just
listening to rebuttals that the
cherry-pick comments because the context
of what's Paul what Paul is saying about
if you were on a rape trial he would
vote to acquit the the male that's
accused no matter the evidence presented
that entire article that he wrote what
was really interesting food for thought
and I do recommend anyone who you know
thinks that's a horrible comment read
the entire article and and no doubt he's
you know angry and in the way he's
explaining his point and he's reacting
from that anger and also trying to
incite anger in the reader but you know
I think the the criticisms of Paul
whenever I watched feminist
documentaries I don't see those
criticisms of well what about when
Gloria Steinem said this in 1995 or what
about when Hillary Clinton said this in
1992 you know that the media doesn't
take the same kind of just what's the
word I'm looking for there they're not
as thorough in looking at every comment
that they've said that could be taken
offensively and asking the filmmaker why
didn't you say when Hillary Clinton said
that the biggest victims of war are
women and children who lose their
husbands and sons you know that that
does sound like a horrible soundbite and
maybe that should be looked at in
feminist documentaries so you know and
then the the fish in bicycle comment by
Gloria Steinem was quoting someone else
but she repeated it so you know that
there was a hashtag kill all men on
Twitter that was going around and being
supported by feminist scholars and
universities you know so I didn't bring
up those in the red pill documentary and
because if we if we just want to sound
cherry-pick sound bites and analyze
those we could have a ten hour
that I think would be hard to sit
through so I tried to make it more about
the ideas and the issues and an
interesting journey for the audience to
go on and there is also this paradox of
you being criticized by male journalists
as a betrayal of of women which I've
seen a few of my female friends who have
a slightly different take on feminism
are often accused by by men of letting
themselves into either internalized
misogyny or some kind of yeah this weird
paradox of okay so as a man you are
devaluing my experience as a woman by
telling me that I'm that I've got the
wrong views and it's that's this sort of
weird paradox catch-22 that it seems
that okay are you not doing exactly the
thing that you're accusing me of doing
by invalidating my experience as a woman
yes yes I don't think I could put it
better than that exactly yeah and you
know I I have had a lot of you know
experiences as a woman that I felt I was
mistreated as a woman and that's why I
became a feminist you know now 15 years
ago so I you know a lot of feminists who
would like to criticize me saying that I
I've been in this bubble where I've only
looked at the men's rights movement and
I didn't look closely enough at feminism
but I did I mean I was a feminist and
never heard about the men's rights
movement for ten years and that was the
real iterator I read and the blog's I
read but even the experiences I had
before coming the coming of feminists I
I know the struggles that women face
absolutely you know more more than I
think a lot of people would realize
because I you know do try to maintain a
level of privacy so yeah I mean for any
male journalist to think that I
I am betraying all women and that I am
engaging and wrong think and and not you
know believing women's stories or hey I
don't
no I yeah I I don't even know how to
respond to people like that because um
yeah I've looked through a lot so and do
you ever ask yourself that question have
I internalized misogyny how am i letting
letting my sisters down any of that hmm
I let my sisters down well one of the
one of the hardest parts about releasing
the film was I felt a loss of sisterhood
and you know I'm not a men's rights
activist and of the women I've met in
the men's rights movement I don't feel
like I'm a part of a sisterhood so I
haven't found this sisterhood since
taking away the label feminists from
myself I I don't feel like I fit into
any kind of sisterhood group now you
know I met some women and a lot of them
would call themselves egalitarian or
equalist or humanists and I think I am
close to the way they think but but
there's not the same kind of camaraderie
that I experienced in feminism and I
don't think I let the sisterhood down
because I think there are plenty of
people who are fighting for valid
women's rights you know sex trafficking
and maternity leaves and you know a lot
of issues that I do want to see address
and people are talking about them and
having conferences for them so I know
that work is being done and I'm not
preventing that work from being done but
you know I think in the way that I am
helping the sisterhood is possibly in
relationships I think the women who have
watched the red pill movie who were self
identifying feminists have really
benefited from opening their eyes to
men's issues and seeing their own male
relationships in new light and so you
know I think I have done a lot for women
another criticism that people have of
the film is sort of why are you showing
all of these angry guys you know that's
why a lot of feminists become
as they've had some personal experience
that enrages them and possibly
rightfully so you know there's I think
when people are really involved in
gender politics or a movement on any
side of the fence
usually it's it's coming from a very
personal place maybe even a place that
it's too hard for them to talk about and
discuss so all you're seeing is the the
bubbles on the surface of what's boiling
underneath and you know I think to write
off activists as just angry whiners or
you know crybabies or ferment so it's
activists that they need a man up or
something like that you know it actually
just kind of justifies what or it
validates and supports what they're
saying is that we we do have this
resistance to having compassion for men
and men's issues and you know even right
now the men's rights movement is
debating whether they should take men's
rights out of their title and because
it's been smeared so much in the media
that there and the hearing men's rights
makes people scoff and laugh and and so
they're wondering should we rebrand it
as a gender equality movement or
something like that and I think that's
very telling as well that just even
having the word men in a men's group or
a men's forum or any any kind of
organization with the word men in it is
already at a disadvantage and is open to
you know being fired at and so you know
I think that's worth looking into and
thinking about that why why is our
society so willing to make money mend
the butt of all jokes and that's
acceptable and you know for truly for
gender equality shouldn't we care about
all genders the me2 moment happened very
soon after releasing the film what did
you personally make of that
oh well the me to movement did you post
me too we know I didn't I think I think
it's good that the movement started if
it helps a lot of women open up about
their their story and and their issues
and feel more accepted and embraced and
speaking about those stories with their
friends or family I think the danger of
the movement is in the language and
identifying only female victims and male
perpetrators and when there have been
people have come forward wanting to
participate in the hashtag me to
movement as a male victim or accusing a
female perpetrator I think you know
there's been a lot of disappointing you
know reactions to that where they are
not openly embraced and and given the
same kind of treatment as a female
victim with a male perpetrator is given
so I think you know just discussing
these issues is really important and I
have you know sexual assault and
harassment was definitely one of the
issues that made me a feminist so I have
a big soft spot for that issue and even
my first documentary called daddy I do
about sex education largely talked about
sexual assault and abuse and rape and
you know these horrible stories that I
know have been going on far longer than
the me to movement has come out so you
know I know it's prevalent and it sort
of increasingly feels like the culture
at large is a kind of dysfunctional
relationship between men and women like
through the me to movement of times art
movement so that certainly the Trump
Hillary election just looked like it
kind of yeah these gender dynamics were
playing out on the wider stage so my my
question is what does the space on the
other side of that look like
and in a way what I guess we talked
about this is Warren Farrell and mine to
be with him like what seems to be needed
as a kind of one's like relationship
counseling on a on a wife cultural scale
like how do how do you resolve this
debate do you have a sense of what the
space on the other side of these this
dynamic looks like I think the best way
for me to explain my view on that is to
bring it down to a very small experience
which is my relationship with my now
husband over about four weeks we've been
together seven years and the last five
years I've been working on the red pill
movie so he's seen me through quite a
transition what really worked for our
relationship was the first two years of
our relationship I was very much in the
feminist mindset and I did and I'm not
saying this is all feminists and I'm not
trying to you know put down feminists by
saying what kind of feminist I was but I
did most of the talking and he did most
the listening and my moods really set
the stage for how home life was going to
be so if I was happy as I say happy wife
happy life that was pretty much the case
I I did the complaining and he did the
resolving and I had a lot to complain
about and mostly it was housework and
what I thought were roles put on me by
the patriarchy expected gender roles of
doing the dishes in the laundry and
cleaning even though we're both working
roughly the same amount hours I may work
at eight-hour day and he would work on
11 or 12 hour a day but we get home and
and it was I thought expected that I
would have dinner ready in the house
clean and I really resented that but he
was also paying most of the bills
because he did make more money and I saw
that as another effect of the patriarchy
and
you know I did believe in the pay gap as
being discrimination against women at
the time I no longer believe that to be
you know the short story of that but
then I started making the red pill movie
and a lot changed with that not only
starting to hear men's issues and
realizing all the ways that I have
privilege as a woman a white woman in
today's society but also seeing all the
ways that men really are disadvantaged
how would you explain that that you the
privilege that you have as a white woman
cuz that what some people won't
understand what you mean by that or will
react against it I well certainly if we
had children I have I would have a lot
of advantages there especially if you
were going through a divorce but also
social reactions if I were to take my
kids to the playground alone there's no
real question about you know me being on
my phone or taking photos of them and
walking along with them but if a man
were to take his kids to the to the park
and be taking photos of them on his
phone there could be and there have been
police called on fathers doing that
let's say yeah in the dating world
there's a lot of advantages you know I
mean Warren throw maybe talk to you a
bit about that but that men still have
the risk of approaching and hitting on
women for the potential of a date
whereas women are I have to say yes or
no and get that privilege and and I when
I started to think would I rather be in
the position of having to approach
someone for a potential relationship
versus be approached I would rather be
approached and and it does feel like the
power position to just say yes or no I
mean if you're a royalty that would be
the position you're sitting in not
trying to plead your case and show your
resume so I started to see that meant
that I really do have a lot of issues
that I never thought about before
whether their rights or just societal
and expectations on them obviously
masculinity is is a really great for a
lot of people where they don't know what
is good masculine anymore we hear toxic
put next to the word masculine any more
than we hear good put next to
masculinity or or positive masculinity
so I think guys have a really hard time
right now and and even if I'm you know
in a work space and I'm the only woman
out of you know ten people I I do feel
that power of that my voice is the
female voice in the room and you know I
even making this film the red pill movie
I was probably heard and listened to
more because I was a woman making this
film rather than a white man trying to
make it film about men's rights so you
know that's the culture that we're
living in today and and I'm grateful
that you know my voice as a woman is
valued and heard certainly and but yeah
I do see a lot of issues that men are
facing so so when I started to
understand the issues men face and apply
it to my own relationship I I started to
wonder what my at the time boyfriend was
going through with maybe sleeping five
hours and I working 11 or 12 hours a day
in a laborious job and paying the
majority of the bills and having that
responsibility that if we can't make
rent it's really on his shoulders to
figure that out so after making a red
pill movie it was the first time in my
life that I switched gender roles with
him and not consciously and not
intentionally but it just turned out
that I had a lot more to do for work and
I was it made more sense for him to help
me with my work than for him to work
harder and we support him going to work
so we focused on my work and he became
the the homemaker type of gender role
where he would take care of the
and do the cleaning in the laundry and
dishes and I noticed a lot of things
that I hadn't seen before such as I
wouldn't notice when he did those kind
of tasks around the house and he would
start saying did you see I did the
dishes and I'd look around the kitchen
like oh yeah oh thanks okay but the
whole day I was focused on paying bills
and getting the finances in order and it
was really stressful and I I realized
how much I hated being the provider I
realized how hard it was to be the
breadwinner and how stressful was and
you know you are thinking months ahead
and what is the financial plan whereas
you know back when I didn't have to
worry about the finances I was feeling
underappreciated for for cooking the
dinners but you know going to into both
roles now I see that that both really
have a lot to be stressed about and
worried about and and both really just
want to be appreciated by the other and
recognized for their contributions to
the household so long story short I
think moving forward for the genders and
for relationships is really trying to
understand how the other person is
walking in their own shoes and what
they're going through and the struggles
they face and the stresses they have
day-to-day and the contributions they do
make and you know that's another thing
is I've I now see so all the sacrifices
that men make for our society whether
it's the road work and the power lines
or the soldiers you know I have family
members in the military and and war
makes me extremely uncomfortable so I
usually just choose to never think about
it but when I really do start to think
about the way that they're putting their
lives on the line for people they don't
even know but a country they believe in
it's really powerful and it you know
when you really think about it you can't
help but get teary-eyed because it's
they are they are doing so much for our
society and for their families and it's
just you know it really saddens me that
so many
men do go unappreciated in and I hate
that women went underappreciated when
they were you know the 50s housewife but
I think we've changed positively in a
new direction for women and I would like
to see that happen for men as well yeah
I guess for me it's that a space needs
to be opened up that we we do listen to
each other that and what you were doing
with that with the film was showing
there is another side to this and this
is the same journey I guess that Warren
Farrell went on that he was a big player
in the in the women's liberation
movement in the 70s and then started at
the same time setting up men's groups
and saying and then the stories he heard
and there kind of turned him on to
realizing wow there are some stories
that are not being heard men's issues
with custody and wanted to be there for
their children and not being allowed to
be and all of these sort of things
and but it was when he was trying to
bring those stories into into the what
was then the women's moving the same
look there are these stories they're not
being heard as well
suddenly they weren't interested he was
sort of pushed out so I guess for me
it's like in any dysfunctional
relationship the only solution is to
hear both sides of the story and have a
dialogue between those two definitely
and you know I think when I was a
feminist the fear was that if you start
giving credit to the men's rights
movement or men's issues that somehow
your issues are gonna be put on the back
burner or that you're no longer gonna be
cared about our funding is no longer
even coming your way for resources and
that that was a big fear of mine you
know I think there is some debate about
whether or not this is a zero-sum game a
lot of people in the men's rights
movement say it's not a zero-sum game
compassion it's not a zero-sum game but
then you can make the argument that
there there is an allotted amount of
finances towards you know any kind of
social issue and if we are going to care
and talk about men's issues and try to
find ways to help them which may need a
lot of funding where's that money going
to come from
so it's not an easy thing and I think
there that's why there is so much
resistance to the men's rights argument
is fear over funding and and time to
care about these issues and err time to
talk about these issues and and also
when you start realizing that men have
so many issues of their own you can't
really say it's it's one group an
entirety that's oppressed by the other
group now we're talking about we're all
on this together we all have issues to
care about if we're all if we all have
issues is that going to just make them
like there's a tie there is no game
there is no race it's just a tie and now
our are people not going to care about
any of the issues because there's not an
enemy with a victor I also as Paul Elam
has shown that anger and polarization
does drive people to to cover the issues
and which is which is quite I guess
disappointing in a way for me is that it
does seem that it's a useful tactic to
be able to drum up anger and response
and reactivity yeah rather than creating
a space for a genuine dialogue yeah and
especially with social media and
everything at the moment yeah and and
the you know the best way to make a
group organize and work together and
have passion about their cause is to
have a common enemy
so if men's rights activists are not the
enemy of feminists what is gonna be the
enemy there needs to be something
identified to keep that that machine
running so maybe there is an an enemy
that we can find that is that is
preventing women from having equal
rights and and I think that's the
distinction that a lot of people need to
look at when listening to feminist
arguments is that equal rights or are
they looking for ways women to have an
advantage over men like in family court
you know do we want shared custody
or or feminist group really fighting for
primary custody for the mother in all
cases so if we're looking at equal
rights and there's something preventing
that from happening let's identify what
is that thing but I don't think it's the
men's rights movement preventing women
from having equal rights you know as far
as men's rights activist what's
preventing men's rights activists from
having equal rights you know and there's
a lot of debate about could the word
rights be used or is it just issues but
there are rights that are being denied
for men that women do have at least in
the u.s. with genital integrity you know
it is outlawed that a girl be
circumcised but boys there is there is
no limitation or restriction on that DNA
testing should you as a person have the
right to know that you are a father or
that the child is in fact yours which
are different story lines to know you
have a child you know there are many
women who get pregnant leave the state
and never tell the father that he is in
fact the father so should that be a
right
you know we've feminism never defined
that as a right because they only looked
at women's rights and that wasn't a part
of the agenda but I would consider that
a human right to know that you're a
parent but only men have to deal with
that problem
so there are rights that are being
tonight for men and who or what is
preventing that from happening
I think men's rights activists to do
have a lot of valid points to make that
feminism and the the mainstream view of
gender politics is really the feminist
ideology and they do have the most
funding they do have you know a lot of
people who become journalists or
university professors are feminists are
self identifying feminists or even self
identifying radical feminists so those
are positions of power in university in
the media
politicians so you know I think men's
rights activists may have a valid point
to make about that Cassie thank you very
much thank you
this film is part of a series from rebel
wisdom on the subject of men and women
including an interview with Warren
Farrell we used to have a battle of the
sexes that's been historical but now we
no longer have a battle of the sexes we
have a war in which only one side has
shown up and with Hannah milling the
creator of the viral film from women to
men I am a woman
[Music]
who has been hurt by men I'm a woman who
has hurt men who has heard men